‎-嗨 ‎-嗨
-[doctor] Hi. -Hi.
‎你在见证一个历史性的时刻
[narrator] You're witnessing an historic moment.
‎现在 全世界都在寻找 ‎攻克这种冠状病毒的方法
Right now, there's a worldwide hunt for ways to fight this coronavirus.
‎科学家在尝试各种方案
Scientists are trying everything,
‎从现有药物到新疗法
from existing medicines to new therapies.
‎但最有可能终结这场全球大流行病的
But the most likely way we'll end this pandemic
‎还是疫苗
is a vaccine.
‎2020年3月16日
On March 16th, 2020,
‎第一种疫苗投入测试
the first one was tested.
‎我是珍妮佛哈勒
I'm Jennifer Haller,
‎我是第一个 ‎接种试验用新冠肺炎疫苗的人
and I was the first person to receive an experimental COVID-19 vaccine.
‎我们之前开发试验用疫苗的速度 ‎相当快
[narrator] We've made other test vaccines pretty quickly.
‎非典疫苗用了20个月
One for SARS took 20 months,
‎埃博拉疫苗用了七个月
one for Ebola, seven months,
‎寨卡疫苗 大约六个月
and one for Zika, around six months.
‎但这一次破了记录
But this vaccine candidate crushed those records.
‎只用65天就做出来了
It was made in just 65 days.
‎但是 要想终结这场全球大流行病
If it's going to end this pandemic, though,
‎还有很长的路要走
it's got a long way still to go.
‎每一种潜在有效疫苗 ‎都要走过一条艰难的道路
See, any potential vaccine has a difficult path ahead,
‎这条路漫长曲折 充满挑战和考验
a long and twisting course full of challenges and trials.
‎在美国
In the US,
‎一种疫苗从开始到最终完成
typically it takes a vaccine candidate a decade or so
‎通常需要十年
to make it from start to finish,
‎90%的疫苗跑不到终点
and around 90% fail to complete it.
‎我们没有那么多时间
We don't have that kind of time.
‎每天都有人死亡
Every day, people are dying,
‎经济损失越来越大
and the economic losses are mounting.
‎专家希望 ‎2021年就能有疫苗普遍推广
Experts are hoping a vaccine can be widely available in 2021.
‎要实现这个目标
To pull that off,
‎就必须用破纪录的速度 ‎走完研发过程的每一个阶段
it will have to get through every stretch of this course in record time.
‎这是对人与机器的终极考验
[car engines roaring]
[announcer] This is the supreme test of man and machine.
‎很多人从发车线出发
But while many are called to the starting line,
‎但只有不到一半能跑完艰苦的全程
usually less than half finish the grueling drive.
‎幸运的是 已有超过100种备选疫苗 ‎在研发过程中
[narrator] Fortunately, more than 100 vaccine candidates are giving it a shot,
‎全世界的科学家参与了疫苗的开发 ‎有资深大学教授…
made by scientists all over the world, from veterans at universities...
‎我们有很多杰出的科学家
We have a dedicated group of extraordinary scientists
‎夜以继日地不懈工作
that are in the lab day and night.
‎也有大型制药企业
[narrator] ...to pharmaceutical giants...
‎我们有研发团队 人人精神百倍
We have the teams to do this, and everyone is excited.
‎采用已经证明的技术…
[narrator] ...using proven techniques...
‎当然 针对冠状病毒疫苗 ‎我们有一定先发优势
And, of course, with the coronavirus vaccine,
we have a particular head start.
‎…和从来没有试验过的新方法
[narrator] ...and approaches that have never been tested before.
‎大家都在相互竞争
Everybody competes with each other,
‎但最终 只有最优秀的留下来
but eventually, only the very best survive.
‎但是 开发一款疫苗 ‎也要耗费大量金钱…
[narrator] But getting a vaccine is also going to take a lot of money...
‎好的 这里有我们 ‎我们可以让资金快速到位
Okay, here we are. You know, we can get money out really fast.
‎我们可以进行评估
We can do evaluations of these things.
‎现在 我们都在加快速度 ‎在全世界寻找最佳方案
Now we're all trying to step up
and look all over the world for the best ideas.
‎…需要协作
[narrator] ...and collaboration.
‎全球科学界同仁
The entire global scientific community
‎以史无前例的方式走到一起
has come together in a truly unprecedented way.
‎也离不开勇敢的志愿者
[narrator] ...and brave volunteers.
‎我们都感到无助 ‎我觉得 这件事我可以做
We're all feeling so helpless, and this was something that I saw
‎而且很可能会对大家有帮助
that I could do that could potentially make a difference.
‎就这样 他们共同投入了一场 ‎史上最成败攸关的科学竞赛
[narrator] Together, they're in one of the most
high-stakes scientific races in history.
‎我把它比作太空竞赛
I compare this to a space race.
‎众多竞争者 争夺一个未知的目标 ‎“我怎么去火星？”
We have so many contenders reaching for something that was previously unknown.
"How do I get to Mars?"
‎“我怎么去金星？”
"How do I get to Venus?"
‎“我们怎么制造 ‎下一代新冠肺炎疫苗？”
"How do we create the next COVID-19 vaccine?"
‎还有一个重要的问题：
[narrator] And the other big question:
‎我们能在多短的时间里实现？
how fast can we do it?
[theme music playing]
‎现在 我们已经有了病毒
Given the fact that we now have the virus in our hands,
‎我们会开发出疫苗
we will develop a vaccine.
‎我们可以以前所未有的速度行动
[man 1] We can move very fast in ways that have not been previously achieved.
‎一旦疫苗被证明是安全的
[man 2] It's only once that vaccine has been proven to be safe
‎就立刻投入使用
that it'll be allowed out of confinement.
‎他们需要疫苗
[man 3] What they needed was a vaccine,
‎一天没有找到 ‎他们的奋斗就一天不停止
and the fight never stopped till it was found.
‎还有其他病毒需要分离 ‎其他疫苗有待开发
[man 4] There remain other viruses to be isolated, other vaccines to come,
‎他们会成功的
but they will.
‎这种冠状病毒 以及所有病毒 ‎都很难对付
[narrator] This coronavirus, and all viruses, are so hard to fight,
‎原因之一是它们太简单了
in part because they're so simple.
‎它们基本就是一个微小的信息载体
They're basically just little vehicles
‎承载着指导它们进行自我复制的说明
that carry instructions on how to make more of themselves.
‎为了繁衍 它们把这套复制说明 ‎偷偷运进我们的细胞
To reproduce, they smuggle these instructions into our cells
‎强迫我们的细胞工厂制造更多病毒
and force our cellular machinery to make more and more viruses.
‎它们在体内扩散 劫持更多细胞
They spread through the body and hijack more cells,
‎在这个过程中 细胞被破坏
damaging them in the process,
‎我们就生病了
which makes us feel sick.
‎但我们不是没有防御措施
But we're not defenseless.
[alarm blares]
‎我们免疫系统的细胞会找到入侵者 ‎识别出一种标记
-[narrator] Cells in our immune system -[siren wails]
can find the intruder and identify a marker,
‎一种特征鲜明的标记 我们叫它抗原
a distinguishing feature which we call an antigen.
‎然后 它们就行动起来 找到并消灭 ‎任何携带这种抗原的物质
Then they mobilize to seek out and destroy anything with that antigen.
‎我们的免疫系统还会产生一种 ‎叫做抗体的小分子
Our immune system also produces little molecules called antibodies
‎抗体附着于抗原 标记并制服病毒
that stick to that antigen, tagging and subduing the virus.
‎但是 从我们被感染那一天开始
But from the day we're infected,
‎可能需要两周时间 ‎免疫反应才会全面启动
it can take almost two weeks for this response to ramp up,
‎足以让冠状病毒扩散到全身
enough time for this coronavirus to swarm through the body,
‎造成伤害
wreaking havoc.
‎有时候 ‎我们的免疫系统还会反应过度
And sometimes our immune system ramps up too much
‎导致更多伤害
and causes even more harm.
‎有些人伤害太严重
In some people, all this damage becomes overwhelming,
‎导致死亡
and they die.
‎我值一天班 就宣布了六名患者死亡
In one shift, I pronounced six people dead.
‎如果有办法医治 就好了
[narrator] This is where having a treatment would help.
‎有的疗法是注射抗体 ‎也就是那些降服病毒的小分子
Some inject antibodies, those molecules that subdue the virus,
‎或者是在实验室合成的抗体
either synthetic antibodies made in a lab,
‎或是从康复患者血液中分离出的抗体
or from the blood of people who've recovered.
‎有的疗法是对失控的免疫系统 ‎加以控制
Others rein in our immune systems if they're getting out of control.
‎还有的疗法 比如瑞德西韦
And some, like Remdesivir,
‎是进入细胞 阻止病毒自我复制
actually enter our cells to block the virus from copying itself.
‎早期结果显示 ‎它可能可以降低病毒的致命性
Early results showed it could potentially make the virus less deadly.
‎这是一个很重要的概念验证
It is a very important proof of concept,
‎这证明了 一种药物可以阻断病毒
because what it has proven is that a drug can block this virus.
‎但截至五月 还没有一种疗法 ‎能防止人患病
[narrator] But as of May,
none of these treatments can stop a person from getting sick,
‎或阻止病毒人际传播
or spreading this coronavirus to others.
‎疫苗可以做到
A vaccine would,
‎因为疫苗利用了人体
and it does it by taking advantage of something
‎经过数百万年进化而来的一种能力
our bodies have evolved over millions of years:
‎记忆
memory.
‎我们的免疫系统对抗过一种病毒之后 ‎就记住了它的抗原
After it deals with a virus, our immune system remembers the antigens,
‎有时是终生记忆
sometimes forever,
‎有时只能记住一段时间
other times just for a while.
‎我们知道 我们的身体 ‎对其他冠状病毒的记忆长达好几年
We know our bodies can remember these other coronaviruses for a couple years.
‎如果这种冠状病毒的情况类似
So if this coronavirus is similar
‎并且它在几年内再次入侵我们的身体
and it shows up in our bodies again in that time,
‎我们的免疫系统就能更快地作出反应 ‎重拳出击
our immune system can ramp up much faster with overwhelming force,
‎消灭病毒 使我们不至于生病
wiping out the virus before it can make us sick
‎也不至于传染给他人
or spread to someone else.
‎所谓对某病毒免疫 就是这个意思
This is what it means to be immune to a virus.
‎疫苗能让我们免疫
A vaccine makes us immune
‎方法就是安全地告诉我们的身体 ‎某种病毒长什么样
by safely showing the body what a virus looks like,
‎制造一次假的感染 ‎教会身体如何反应
faking this first infection to teach your body how to respond,
‎这样 如果身体遇到真的病毒 ‎就知道该怎么办了
so when it does encounter the real virus, it's ready.
‎没有100%有效的病毒
No vaccine is 100% effective,
‎不是每个人接种疫苗之后 ‎都能彻底免疫
meaning not everyone who receives one will be perfectly immune,
‎但疫苗不需要百试百效 ‎也能终止疫病流行
but vaccines don't need to be perfect to end epidemics.
‎天花曾经是一种高致命性疾病
Smallpox used to be a leading cause of death,
‎麻疹曾经每年杀死数百万人 ‎多数是儿童
and measles killed millions a year, most of them children.
‎但是 多亏有了有效率达到95%的疫苗
But thanks to vaccines that are around 95% effective,
‎我们现在已经消灭了天花
we've wiped out smallpox
‎对抗麻疹也取得了长足进步
and made enormous progress against measles.
‎疫苗制造者希望能造出 ‎这么有效的疫苗
Vaccine makers are hoping to make a vaccine that effective.
‎如果我们只能造出 比如说 ‎有效率为50%的疫苗
If all we could make was a vaccine that, let's say, had 50% efficacy,
‎那么它能防止半数的感染
so it prevented about half of the infections,
‎如果这意味着死亡人数减半 ‎那也是真正的好消息
if that translates into stopping half of the deaths,
that's really good news.
‎事实上 疫苗是人类历史上 ‎最重要的发明之一
[narrator] The fact is,
vaccines are one of the most significant inventions in human history.
‎这个世界上没有太多共识
The world doesn't agree on much,
‎但是 超过90%的人 ‎相信儿童接种疫苗很重要
but more than 90% of all people believe childhood vaccinations are important,
‎这至关重要 因为 要消灭一种传染病
and that's crucial, because to wipe out an infectious disease,
‎你需要全世界多数人口都免疫
you need most people in the world to be immune.
‎这叫群体免疫
It's called herd immunity.
‎一个人感染后存活 或者接种疫苗
The idea is that individuals become immune either by getting infected and surviving,
‎都可实现免疫
or by getting vaccinated.
‎当足够的人实现了免疫
When enough people are immune,
‎病毒就难以传播 速度放慢
the virus has trouble spreading, and slows down.
‎你知道 通过接种疫苗 ‎你不只是保护你自己
You know, you are also protecting by vaccinating yourself
‎也是在保护周围的易感人群
not just yourself, but you are protecting weak members in the community
‎那些可能无法获得疫苗的人
who may not be able to get the vaccine.
‎比如新生儿 老年人 ‎和免疫系统较弱的群体
[narrator] Like newborns, the elderly, and people with weak immune systems.
‎所以这既是自我保护 ‎也是一种利他行为
So it's both an act of protecting yourself and it's also an act of altruism.
‎所以 打败一种传染病 ‎需要全世界通力合作
[narrator] So defeating an infectious disease
requires the whole world coming together,
‎在对抗新冠肺炎的竞赛中 ‎全世界的团结合作史无前例
and in the COVID-19 race, the world has come together like never before.
‎截至五月 有100多种疫苗正在研制中
Out of the over 100 candidates in the race in May,
‎一半以上在北美 17种在中国
almost half are in North America, and 17 are in China.
‎大家的经费来源也各不相同
And they're funded in different ways,
‎多数是由私人企业支持
most by private industry.
‎但最主要的区别还是他们的疫苗平台
But the main difference between them is their vaccine platform,
‎如何告诉人体病毒长什么样
how they're showing the body what the virus looks like.
‎有的疫苗把弱化了的病毒注射入人体
Some vaccines inject a weakened version of the virus into the body.
‎它已不能复制或造成伤害 ‎但仍然携带有抗原
It can't reproduce or do damage but it still has that antigen,
‎这样 我们的免疫系统就可以 ‎学会如何识别目标
so our immune system can learn what to watch out for.
‎我们针对脊髓灰质炎、麻疹
That's how we vaccinate against polio,
‎流行性腮腺炎和风疹
the measles, mumps, and rubella,
‎水痘、轮状病毒还有流感的疫苗
chicken pox, rotavirus,
‎就是这样
and for the flu.
‎这是至今为止最成熟有效的方法
This is by far our most tried-and-true method,
‎但是这种方法很慢
but it's a slow way to do it.
‎我们要在其他活体细胞 比如鸡蛋中 ‎培养病毒几个月
We have to grow the virus for months in other living cells, like chicken eggs,
‎这种方法我们已经用了几十年
a method we've been using for decades.
‎我们就叫它第一代疫苗吧
We'll call these the first-generation vaccines,
‎截至五月初 ‎有九种第一代疫苗参与试验
and there are nine in the race as of early May.
‎其他科学家在尝试一种新方法
Other scientists are trying a newer approach.
‎他们不注射完整的冠状病毒
Instead of the whole coronavirus,
‎而是只注射抗原
they're giving the body just an antigen,
‎他们认为 这就足以激活免疫反应
a piece they think will activate the immune response.
‎这些抗原也需要培养 ‎有时是在酵母细胞中培养
Those antigens also need to be grown, sometimes in yeast cells,
‎或者是附着于另一个无害的病毒
or attached to another harmless virus.
‎乙肝疫苗就是这个原理
This is how the vaccine for hepatitis B works,
‎百日咳和脑膜炎也是这样
and for whooping cough, and meningitis B.
‎我们叫这种疫苗第二代疫苗
We'll call these second-generation vaccines,
‎在攻克新冠肺炎的竞赛中 ‎第二代疫苗应用最广 现有72个备选
and they're the most popular kind in the COVID-19 race, with 72 candidates.
‎最后 还有一种全新的疫苗
Finally, there's a brand new type of vaccine
‎它完全不使用病毒的任何成分
that doesn't use any part of the actual virus at all.
‎而只是把病毒的复制信息 ‎传递给我们的身体
Instead, it just gives our bodies the virus's instructions,
‎这些遗传信息片段 ‎能指导我们的细胞生产出抗原
tiny pieces of genetic code that tell our cells to produce the antigens,
‎从而激活免疫反应
which then activate the immune response.
‎这种原理的疫苗 ‎还没有被批准应用于人体
No vaccine using this approach has ever been approved for use in humans.
‎我们可以把这种疫苗称为第三代疫苗
We'll call these the third-generation vaccines,
‎现有27种参与试验
and there are 27 in the race.
‎第三代疫苗不需要培养病毒
Because they don't involve growing any part of any virus,
‎所以制造速度可以非常快
they can be made extremely fast.
‎这支破纪录的疫苗 ‎就是第三代备选疫苗
This record-breaking vaccine was a third-generation candidate
‎来自美国莫德纳公司
from a US company called Moderna.
‎但制造一种备选疫苗并不难
But making a vaccine candidate isn't the hard part.
‎难的是下一步
This next phase is.
‎临床试验
Clinical trials.
[engines rev]
‎他们全速前进
[announcer] And they're up to speed.
‎传统上 临床试验分三个阶段
[narrator] Traditionally, there are three phases.
‎首先 科研团队给少数人注射疫苗
First, teams give their vaccines to a small group of people,
‎等几个月 ‎看看他们有没有危险的不良反应
wait a few months, and see if any of them report dangerous side effects.
‎如果一切都好
If everything looks good,
‎疫苗就进入下一阶段 ‎给大约200人接种
the vaccine moves on and is given to a couple hundred people,
‎还是观察有无危险的不良反应
again, to see if there are any dangerous side effects,
‎但也要观察人的免疫系统 ‎是否被调动起来
but also to see if people's immune systems ramp up.
‎这需要等更久 通常几个月
That involves more waiting, usually months.
‎然后 疫苗进入三期试验
Then the candidate moves on to the third test,
‎数千人接种 ‎第三次确保没有不良反应
where thousands are vaccinated to triple-check for side effects
‎同时观察效果
and see how well it works.
‎这又要等几个月 甚至几年
That's another few months or years of waiting.
‎这不同于药物试验
This isn't like testing a drug
‎你让患者服药
where you give it to people with a disease
‎看他们是否好转
and see if it makes them better.
‎你是要把疫苗给没病的人
You're giving it to people who don't have a disease,
‎然后观察他们是否仍然不得病
and then checking later to see if they still don't have the disease.
‎正常情况下 整个过程会历时四年
In normal times, this whole process can take around four years,
‎针对五千人进行试验
testing around 5,000 people.
‎但是 疫苗开发者希望 ‎有些试验可以同步进行
But vaccine developers are hoping to do some of this testing simultaneously,
‎还是测这么多人 ‎但都在18个月里完成
still testing the same number of people, but all in around 18 months.
‎这就是为什么 ‎有的备选疫苗进展如此迅速
It's how some candidates are moving so quickly.
‎药监局已经批准莫德纳疫苗 ‎进入二期临床试验
The FDA has cleared the Moderna vaccine for phase two of its trial.
‎莫德纳以破纪录的速度前进
[reporter 1] Moderna moving at record speed.
‎中国已经批准了另一项临床试验
China's already given approval for another clinical trial.
‎现在已进入二期阶段
It's now at the second phase.
‎目前 最有希望的疫苗
The vaccine, uh, that is most promising right now
‎来自牛津大学
is the one from Oxford University.
‎-一二期合并 ‎-神速
-That has merged phase one and phase two. -...which is speedy.
‎这个阶段的竞赛不能更快了 ‎这是有原因的
[narrator] This stage of the race can't go any faster, for good reason.
‎不进行所有这些试验
[Kirchhelle] Without running through all of these trials,
‎就推出疫苗
it would be absolutely unethical
‎让普罗大众接种 ‎那是严重违反科学伦理的
to roll out a vaccine potentially to the entire global population,
‎因为你可能会造成真正的伤害
because you could do some real harm there.
‎今天 我们的士兵不必担心黄热病了
[news reel announcer] Our men today are safe against yellow fever.
‎几滴疫苗 ‎就能带给他们可靠长效的免疫
A few drops of vaccine will give them dependable and lasting immunity.
‎二战期间 ‎同盟国士兵接种了黄热病疫苗
[narrator] During World War II,
Allied soldiers were vaccinated for yellow fever.
‎数千人罹患黄疸和肝炎 有人死亡
Thousands developed jaundice and hepatitis, and some died.
‎这本是可以避免的
That should never have happened.
‎疫苗开发者如果做了研究
If the vaccine makers had done their research,
‎他们就会发现 ‎早在1885年就有此类不良反应的报告
they would have discovered reports of these side effects dating back to 1885.
‎到了20世纪50年代
Then in the 1950s,
‎劣质疫苗导致四万人感染脊髓灰质炎
some poorly made vaccines infected 40,000 people with polio,
‎约200人死亡
and killed around 200.
‎史称卡特事件
Known as "the Cutter incident,"
‎美国政府随后 ‎加强了对疫苗生产的监管
it led the US government to tighten requirements for vaccine manufacturers.
‎未经严格的安全考察 绝不会审批
Nothing is licensed without undergoing extremely stringent safety considerations.
‎即便是审批之后 也继续受到监督
And even after it's licensed, the vaccine continues to be monitored.
‎今天 根据美国政府数据
[narrator] Today, according to the US government,
‎每投放百万份疫苗
for every million doses of vaccine that are distributed,
‎只有一个人因严重不良反应得到赔偿
only one person is compensated for serious side effects.
‎疫苗的审批门槛极高 ‎因为接种它的是健康的人
Vaccines need to pass an extra-high bar because they're given to healthy people.
‎关系到安全和效果 我们不能走捷径
[Hatchett] What we can't do is take shortcuts
where safety and effectiveness are concerned.
‎我想有办法精简一些环节
I think there are ways to streamline some things
‎更多工作可以同步进行
and do more things in parallel,
‎但这会很难
but it's going to be tough,
‎好比精心编排的舞蹈
and it's going to be a carefully orchestrated dance.
‎不是一件事完成再做下一件事
Rather than running everything in series
‎也不是一个人去做所有的步骤
and having just one person doing each of these steps along the way,
‎而是投入整个团队
whole teams of people have been put there
‎确保维持同样的质量和安全标准
to ensure that we still maintain the same quality and safety.
‎但是 有的团队有先发优势
[narrator] But some teams did have a head start here,
‎因为这不是第一个冠状病毒
because this isn't the first coronavirus,
‎也不是 ‎第一个引发疫苗竞赛的冠状病毒
or the first coronavirus to inspire a race for a vaccine.
‎非典的影响
[reporter 2] The impact of SARS.
‎非典已经传遍世界
[reporter 3] The SARS disease has spread across the world.
‎针对中东呼吸综合征
[reporter 4] The battle against an outbreak
‎简称MERS的战斗 在韩国继续
of Middle East Respiratory Syndrome, or MERS, continues in South Korea.
‎非典和MERS病毒大爆发时
[narrator] When SARS and MERS viruses caused outbreaks,
‎很多科学家就开始研制疫苗
many scientists got to work on vaccines,
‎包括牛津大学的一个团队
including a team at Oxford University.
‎我们对冠状病毒和它们的生物学机制 ‎有了很多了解
We've learnt a lot about coronaviruses and their biology,
‎事实上 就是因为上两次大爆发
actually, because of the last two big outbreaks.
‎2018年 牛津大学的一种很有希望的 ‎MERS疫苗进入人体试验阶段
[narrator] In 2018, Oxford University got a promising MERS candidate
into human trials,
‎希望能避免 ‎这种罕见冠状病毒再次爆发
hoping to stop the next outbreak of this rare coronavirus.
‎可是一年之后 ‎这种新型冠状病毒出现了
But then a year later, this latest coronavirus broke out.
‎因为二者比较相似
Because it was similar,
‎科研团队可以比较容易地把 ‎他们的MERS疫苗改造成新冠肺炎疫苗
the team easily adapted their MERS vaccine into a COVID-19 one.
‎我们走了一条重要的捷径
And so that has really been a major shortcut that we've had,
‎而不需要再回去 从一张白纸开始
by not having to go back to the drawing board and start again.
‎他们快速通过一期试验
[narrator] They sped through the first phase of trials,
‎准备今年夏天进入后续试验阶段
putting them on track to begin the next phases in the summer.
‎我们不确定 ‎是不是一切都能按计划进行
We don't know for certain that that will all go to plan,
‎但是如果一切顺利 那么今年秋天
but if it does, then it's certainly possible
‎完全可能会有几百万份疫苗生产出来
that there could be millions of doses available in the autumn.
‎很不幸 牛津大学的故事并不普遍
[narrator] Unfortunately, Oxford's story is uncommon.
‎彼得候特茲几年前也研制出一种 ‎很有希望的非典疫苗
Peter Hotez also made a promising coronavirus vaccine for SARS years ago.
‎一切都很顺利 可是后来 经费中断了
It was all going well, and then the grant ended.
‎我们想 “都走了这么远了
And we thought, "Well, we've gone this far.
‎我们只好再筹钱 ‎把它推进到临床阶段”
We'll just get funding to move it into clinical trials."
‎很遗憾 我们筹不到钱
And unfortunately, we couldn't.
‎很多很有希望的疫苗就这样夭折了
[narrator] This happened to so many promising vaccines
‎这个阶段因此也被称为 ‎“疫苗的死亡之谷”
that this stage is often called "the Vaccine Valley of Death."
‎这些科学家以破纪录的速度
Of these vaccine candidates
‎研制的备选疫苗
that scientists race to make in record time,
‎只有埃博拉疫苗跑到了终点
only Ebola reached the finish line.
‎因为一旦疫情结束 资金也就中断了
Because when these outbreaks ended, so did the funding.
‎每次灾难性的疫情之后
After every catastrophic pandemic or epidemic,
‎我都会说： ‎“也许这一次终于能看到改变了
I say, "Maybe this is the one that moves the needle
‎终于能看到公共财政拨款了”
and gets public funding in place."
‎2003年非典之后我就这么说
And I said that after SARS in 2003,
‎2009年H1N1之后我又这么说
I said it after H1N1 in 2009,
‎2012年MERS之后 我又这么说
I said it after MERS in 2012,
‎2014年埃博拉之后 我又这么说
I said it after Ebola in 2014,
‎2016年兹卡病毒之后 我又这么说
after Zika in 2016, and I'll say it again.
‎彼得的新冠肺炎疫苗是 ‎基于他的非典疫苗改造而成的
[narrator] Peter's COVID-19 candidate is based on his SARS candidate.
‎但如果当年就能进行测试
But if he had been able to test it back then...
‎我们现在可能已经做完安全测试了
We would have had the safety testing potentially finished,
‎那就非同小可 是不是？
and that's not insignificant, right?
‎所以 我们失去了那个机会 太可惜了
So that's too bad that we lost that opportunity.
‎2017年
[narrator] In 2017,
‎在盖茨基金会的部分资助下 一群人
a group of people funded in part by the Gates Foundation
‎聚集一堂 尝试解决这个问题
came together to fix this.
‎很不幸 虽然各种疫病流行的
Well, unfortunately, even though there's a substantial risk
‎风险很高
of various types of epidemics,
‎但是人们却没有足够动力 ‎去生产出防患未然的产品
there's not a natural incentive for people to build products that anticipate that.
‎我们必须把政府和基金会整合起来
You've got to bring governments and foundations together
‎创造一个合理的激励机制
to create the right incentive structure.
‎他们把这个组织命名为CEPI
[narrator] They call themselves CEPI,
‎流行病预防创新联盟
The Coalition for Epidemic Preparedness Innovations.
‎CEPI的作用就是把资金整合起来 ‎成为一个资金池
[Hatchett] What CEPI is,
is it aggregates funding and creates a pool of funds
‎去支持疫苗的研发
to support vaccine development.
‎这样 我们可以作为诚实中间人
So we can play fair broker
‎拿着这笔几十亿美元的资金 ‎确保在世界范围内
and take those billions that are available for tools for the world
‎把它用在正确的地方
and make sure they go to the right place.
‎截至五月初 已有九个 ‎新冠肺炎备选疫苗获得CEPI支持
[narrator] As of early May, CEPI is behind nine COVID-19 candidates,
‎包括两个领先的疫苗：
including two of the early front-runners:
‎牛津大学的新疫苗和莫德纳疫苗
Oxford's new candidate, and Moderna's.
‎这两种疫苗 ‎以及一种中国疫苗的成功
And it's the success of those two candidates,
and one from China,
‎让专家看到希望 认为18个月后 ‎就可能有一种疫苗获得批准
that give experts hope that we can have a vaccine approved in 18 months,
‎但这还不是竞赛的终点
but that isn't the end of the race.
‎还差得远呢
Not even close.
[car engines roaring]
‎他们又进入下一圈的角逐
[announcer] And around they go once more,
‎加速前进 轮胎几乎起火
burning tires down to the fabric as they pour on the coal.
‎别忘了 要终结这场全球大流行病 ‎我们需要达到群体免疫
[narrator] Remember, to end this pandemic, we need to reach herd immunity.
‎针对这种冠状病毒 专家估计
And for this coronavirus, experts estimate
‎需要全世界至少60%的人口实现免疫
that means at least 60% of the world needs to become immune.
‎那就是将近80亿人的60%
That's 60% of almost eight billion people.
‎需要生产几十亿支疫苗？
[interviewer] Billions of vaccines need to be made?
‎是的
That's correct.
‎在世界历史上 ‎我们从来没有生产过十亿支疫苗
We've never produced a billion doses of a vaccine in the history of the world.
‎数十亿支疫苗 这是破天荒的
[Gates] You're in a new regime when you talk about billions of a vaccine.
‎我们任何疫苗也没有量产过几十亿支
We don't make billions of any vaccine.
‎我们可以生产几亿支
We make hundreds of millions,
‎但那也需要几十年 就连药瓶
but those we've had decades to work on. And even the bottles,
‎也是特殊的药品级玻璃
that's a special, pharmaceutical-grade glass,
‎世界上没有那么多
the world doesn't have enough of that.
‎首先
[narrator] Just to start with,
‎要生产十亿支疫苗 ‎你需要有很多工厂
to make a billion doses, you need a lot of factories.
‎但是每种疫苗都需要不同类型的工厂
But each type of vaccine requires a different kind of factory,
‎要让足够多的工厂提高产量 ‎可能需要几年时间
and ramping up production in enough factories can take years.
‎不过 很多大型制药企业有条捷径
But a lot of the giants have a shortcut.
‎他们让工厂现在就开工生产
They have the factories to start production now.
‎我们有一个大工厂 完全可以开工
We have one big plant which is fully operational.
‎可以产出三亿支疫苗
So that can spit out 300 million vaccines.
‎现在 我们正在世界各地 ‎快速建设新工厂
Now we are very quickly setting up additional plants in the world.
‎但是 较新型的疫苗 ‎没有几家工厂能生产 甚至根本没有
[narrator] But the newer types of vaccines don't have many, or any, factories yet,
‎所以 有人已经开始在 ‎不同的备选疫苗上下注
so some are placing bets on candidates now,
‎为他们认为有可能通过测试的疫苗 ‎筹建工厂
building factories for the ones they think might survive trials.
‎毕竟 那些投资至多几十亿 ‎却可以省下几万亿
After all, those investments are, at most, billions to save trillions.
‎就算我们可以生产出那么多疫苗
[narrator] And even if we can make that many doses,
‎我们还需要把疫苗送到 ‎世界各地的人们那里
we'll still need to get the vaccine to people all over the world,
‎这时候 政治因素就会成为障碍
and that's when politics can get in the way.
‎我们有一种疫苗 我们相信能保护
[Andrew Cuthbertson] We have a specific vaccine that we believe
‎数百万人不被新型H1N1病毒感染
will be able to protect millions of people against this new H1N1 flu.
‎2009年猪流感疫情期间
[narrator] During the swine flu epidemic in 2009,
‎一家澳大利亚公司率先研制出疫苗
an Australian company was among the first to make a vaccine,
‎政府要求他们首先卖给澳大利亚人
and the government made them sell to Australians first.
‎加拿大也采取类似做法
Canada made a similar move.
‎尽管美国承诺捐赠一部分
And while the US promised to donate some of its supply,
‎但他们直到疫情结束才捐出
they waited until the epidemic was over.
‎所以 疫苗在哪里生产 很重要
So it matters where a vaccine is made.
‎疫苗民族主义
Vaccine nationalism. That is real.
‎已经有迹象表明 ‎有人想买下正在研发最有希望的
There are early signs that people are trying to buy by the biotech companies
‎疫苗的生物科技公司
that have lead contenders.
‎狭隘地把国家利益摆在最优先位置
There's a long tradition of narrowly putting
‎这种做法由来已久
national interest above others,
‎显然 这样做的人通常是有钱人
and that's obviously often correlated with people who have the money.
‎世界各国领导人联合呼吁展开合作
[narrator] World leaders have come together
and called for cooperation.
‎科学无国界
[in German] Science is never national. Science serves mankind.
‎大家承诺确保机会均等 这是关键
[in English] The commitment to ensuring equal access is the key.
‎在全世界有需要的人
Victory against this virus cannot be declared
‎都能获得有效的疫苗和药品之前
before effective vaccines and therapeutics are made available
‎不能说针对病毒的战斗已经胜利
to all in need around the world.
‎可是截至5月
[narrator] But as of May, the US hasn't been one of them.
‎谁能得到疫苗 也取决于价格
Who can get a vaccine will also depend on its price.
‎要多少钱？富裕国家应该多花钱吗？
How much should it cost? Should rich countries pay more?
‎贫穷国家应该少付一点吗？
Should, you know, poorer countries pay less?
‎另外 如果疫苗是 ‎一家大型制药公司研发的
And also, if this vaccine is developed by a major pharmaceutical company,
‎这家公司应该被允许 ‎通过疫苗获得多少收益？
how much money is this company allowed to make off this vaccine?
‎别忘了 这些疫苗多数是私人资助的
[narrator] Remember, most of these vaccines are funded privately,
‎根据一些疫苗制造者的股价上涨情况
and based on how some vaccine makers' stocks have risen,
‎很显然 有些人要发大财了
some people clearly see a potential windfall ahead.
‎但目前 一些公司 比如强生
But so far, some companies like Johnson & Johnson
‎已经承诺廉价销售他们的疫苗
have promised to make their vaccine affordable,
‎低至每支10美元
as little as $10 a dose.
‎这很关键 因为只有接种到几十亿人 ‎疫苗才算成功了
And that's critical, because a vaccine can only win if it gets to billions of people,
‎其中包括向那些无力购买的人提供
including those who can't afford it.
‎要让全世界足够多的人接种
So to vaccinate enough of the world,
‎我们需要不止一个优胜者
we'll actually need more than one winner.
-[engines roaring] -[crowd cheering]
‎这场竞赛不是不同疫苗间的竞赛
[narrator] This race isn't really between the candidates.
‎而是人类和病毒之间的竞赛
It's between humanity and this virus,
‎这个让经济停滞 ‎让全世界数十万人丧生的
that simple little vehicle that's paralyzed economies
‎简单的生物信息载体
and ended hundreds of thousands of lives around the world.
‎要战胜它 ‎我们必须做从没有做过的事：
We can only beat it by doing what we've never done before:
‎以破纪录的速度 ‎为所有人制造出一种疫苗
making a vaccine for everyone in record time.
["Race For the Prize" playing]
♪ Two scientists are racing For the good of all mankind ♪
♪ Both of them side-by-side So determined ♪
♪ Locked in heated battle For the cure that is their prize ♪
♪ But it's so dangerous ♪
♪ But they're determined ♪